[Music]
Let me just say good morning again. It
was wonderful to travel for the
convocation or the commissioning that
was done um just a week ago on Saturday.
And I think that is probably the last
time I will ever wear that cape. I don't
see there being reason to wear and if I
must wear robes, it's unlikely there
would be graduation robes. I would
rather wear my bishop robes as opposed
to the graduation ones. But it is God's
grace and I want to thank the Lord that
this honor was bestowed on me. Uh many
of you have said that you know you have
earned it. The truth be told I have not
earned it because all I have sought to
do is be a servant of the Lord to be
faithful in the work that he has called
me to. There are many many others who
have done greater exemplary things than
I have or ever will. And I am humbled
that God would choose that uh I should
be honored in this way. And so I receive
that honor believing and trusting that
in any ways I can use it to leverage
greater outcomes for the kingdom of God,
I would be happy to do that. And thank
you all for rejoicing and celebrating
that with me. But let's turn to the word
of the Lord and uh reflect on the things
that this month I would like us to focus
on. I was invited by pastor Nick when he
was going on
sabbatical and he asked me would you
please in my absence give um us 3 months
at the Nairobi chapel Gong road. Now you
heard I was at Tuttowala and uh at
Machakos and um I'll soon be traveling
to Kisumu and then to Meu and then to
Embu and then to other places where we
have churches and I need to visit them
and spend time with them. Which is why
I'm not often here. Sometimes people
come and ask me, "Oh, Bishop, how is
retirement?" And I say, "What
retirement? I haven't retired." You
know, I'm still doing the work that God
called me to. It's just that I'm not
present here on Gong Road. And so when
when Nick, Pastor Nick had, you know,
called me uh requested me to um spend
time with this congregation, I thought
in this second time because I was here
in February and I'll be here again in
September. In this second opportunity, I
want us to talk about
prayer. And I'll tell you why I chose
that we would focus on prayer. It is
because at the time that I was ordained
to be a
bishop,
28 years of having pastored this
congregation from its inception
until
2017. I asked the Lord a
question after the ordination and the
question was, "Lord, if I could do this
all over again, what would you have me
do
different?" And without a shadow of
doubt, I felt the Lord
impress an answer on my heart to that
question. And the answer was
pray. And as I reflected on it, I
thought, it is true, Lord. I have been
far too busy to pray well. And too many
meetings take place on a weekly basis.
There are too many fires to fight. And
there's reading and sermon preparation
and general work and counseling and
training and raising up people. And I
have not been good at the task of
praying. With a congregation that is the
size of this church at the time that I
left, which was at that time about 4,000
people, there was no way I could keep up
with what was going on in every corner
of this compound, let alone with the
daughter churches that have been
planted. And so I said, Lord, if I could
do this all over
again, I would pray. But I'm not good at
prayer. Prayer isn't my forte. It
doesn't come easily for
me. And because I still have another
chapter to go, another 20, 25 years in
this chapter, Lord, help me
change and help me pray. Teach me to
pray.
I want to depend more on you and to
learn to see things in prayer and not
work things out by my own ability to
strategize and to organize and to
visualize and to make things work. Teach
me the power of prayer and how I can
pray. And the verse that the Lord put on
my heart was John chapter 15 and verse
5. You know this verse? It's the Lord
saying to his disciples, "I am the vine
and you are the branches. If you remain
in me and I in you, you will bear much
fruit. Apart from me, you can do
nothing." I felt deeply convicted by
this because I'd never really been good
at prayer. And so I said, "Help me Lord
and I will live this and I will change
the way I work." That was seven years
ago. And I began by largely trying to
discipline my life and to organize my
life so that I could somehow increase my
prayer capacity. I was disciplined. I
sought to do everything I need to do.
But prayer continued to be difficult for
me.
seven years
ago. But about a year, a year and a
half, I was reflecting back on the
ordination in 2017. And it struck me
that while I had not been paying
attention, while I wasn't looking, God
had actually turned my heart towards
prayer. And I could now say this about a
year and a half ago. I could now say
that I enjoy prayer and I look forward
to praying and I have become so much
more able to pray. Now I'm not there yet
but there is an anticipation when I get
up in the morning to meet with God and
to spend time in prayer with him. My
span of ways to pray have expanded. I
had been taught to pray in one way as a
young believer and I had kept to that
way all through my years of ministry. I
would pray intercessory prayer. I did
not know about the many other prayers
that we can pray for and with and
through. And I want to share some of
them with you because this month I want
to look at three particular prayers of
way forms of prayer that I want to teach
you including what we'll look at today.
Myriad myriads of ways that we can learn
to pray if we are attentive to God. And
this has been true of my life in the
last couple of um months or the last
year and a half. And I'll be telling you
about my rhythms of
prayer because I want this to be
practical and down to earth. Now maybe
to see whether do I really need to be
talking about this. Let me ask you to
turn to the person that you're seated
with who is a friend and who you can
self-disclose to. Okay? If they're not a
friend, talk about the weather or talk
about politics. But if they're a friend,
answer get them to answer this question
and you answer it back in return. And
the question is this. Are you happy and
satisfied with your prayer life as it
exists right now?
I don't know what your neighbors told
you, but in answer to that question, I
would not have said
yes. Ask your neighbor on the scale of 0
to nine. Okay? Zero being there isn't
even a rumor of prayer in my life. Okay?
Um, one being
occasionally when my life is in crisis
and things are falling apart, I remember
to cry out to God. Four being that well,
you know, I do try maybe 10 minutes a
day I pray. And nine being I am super
satisfied with my prayer life. Ask your
neighbor where on that scale they lie.
Joan, I can I can see you trying to
persuade your neighbor neighbor that
you're number nine. And she looks
skeptical.
I think I would have said that my prayer
life in general would have been probably
a number four, number five. I was not
doing well. And as a pastor, I wanted it
to be different. But prayer was hard
work. And so God began to expand my
repertoire of prayer. And I want to
share with you 10 different ways that
you can pray. Now the Bible talks about
20 or 30 or maybe even more. I will
share just briefly 10 that you may have
heard of or maybe you have never really
come across because we're going to begin
to talk about these ways and I want to
coach you in those things that I have
learned in terms of new ways of praying
that have made prayer a delight and
something that I looked forward to.
Probably the most uh common way that we
pray is what is called intercessory
prayer where we intercede. We stand in
the gap and we pray for those in need
around us. When somebody comes and says,
"Pray for my daughter. She's unwell.
We're going to see the medical doctor
tomorrow. They don't look very happy
with what's going on. Please pray." Then
we step into that gap and we plead to
the God in heaven that we worship on
behalf of this girl who is unwell and
whose life may be at risk. That's
intercessory prayer. And it largely
comes from the time when Jesus was asked
by his disciples, Lord, teach us to
pray. And he told them, when you pray,
pray like this. And we're going to look
at that in a little while because today
I want to focus largely on the six
sections of praying intercessory prayers
in their full. Okay. So intercessory
prayer. The second is meditative or
contemplative prayer. This one maybe you
have not heard about where you take a
single verse or two or three verses from
the Bible and your prayer time is spent
meditating on them and on their message
over its place in your life. It's a
quiet prayer. It's a slow prayer because
you're not trying to cover a lot of
ground. you're only dealing with one or
two verses at a time and you spend a
half hour praying those two verses into
the depths of your soul. We'll talk
about that one too a little later on.
The third you've heard about is
deliverance or spiritual warfare prayer
where we battle demonic forces and pray
for the deliverance of those that we
love from such demonic forces. You know,
one of the things you learn about um the
need for spiritual warfare, and it was a
practice of the early church, the
assumption of the early church in the
days after Jesus's crucifixion was that
anyone who came to the Lord had issues
with demons. Somewhere in your life, you
had opened a door to the demonic and to
demonic influence. Now what we learn
from the Bible is I may have opened that
door through something that I chose to
do you know alcohol, pornography or
whatever it is and when I open the door
it's an open invitation for the evil one
to take occupancy to this place this
house that I have opened the door to. It
doesn't always happen. He won't always
step into that space, but we do not
always know what has happened in the
past. And the early church would often
take young believers and it would take
them through deliverance as a matter of,
you know, um, just the way that they
receive people into the kingdom of God,
believing that somewhere in the past you
opened a door or your protector and your
parent and those who are, you know, in
authority over you like a grandparent
opened a door. Now, for us as Africans,
you know what I'm talking about. You're
born as a child and you're taken to the
witch doctor and they pray blessings
over you, their own witch doctor
blessings, and they tie a string around
your wrist. Or in some cultures here in
Kenya, they tie a string around your
waist and they pronounce that you are
protected by that string and those that
it represents, which is often demonic
forces. and you wear this and you don't
even know the meaning of that string. It
was something my grandfather did for me.
Or they cut you with a razor blade and
they put in charms and spells into that
space. Or when you were sick, you were
taken to the doctor and then you were
taken to the witch doctor. He
slaughtered a chicken, took the blood,
you know, rubbed it into your your
illness and whatever. We opened a door
and allowed space for the evil one to
enter into that space. And so there is
need many a times for deliverance and
spiritual warfare. And we do actually do
that here. Um where we take people
through deliverance in a quiet way. Now
some of us know the deliverance that is
bashing a Bible over the head of the one
that we're delivering. Yeah, that works
sometimes, but it sure gives them a
headache and probably lands them in
hospital. There are other ways where
deliverance can take place. And so, you
probably pray frequently enough over
your life and the life of your loved
ones um in terms of spiritual warfare.
The fourth that you rarely ever hear
about is a prayer of lament.
Twothirds of the Psalms in the book of
Psalm are laments to God. And a lament
is a deep and woeful cry to
God to see you and deliver you from the
pain and that which you are going
through. And you have probably been in
that space when a loved one died and in
total
hopelessness, you had nowhere else to
turn but to God and you wept your pain
in his presence. Lament takes place when
a nation is undone. You see this for
example in the book of Jonah when the
king of Nineve heard that God was about
to judge that nation and that city and
he called on all members and citizens of
his nation to put on sackcloths and to
pray and cry to the God of heaven to
have mercy on them. And they cried a
lament asking God's forgiveness and for
his mercy. And God relented from what he
was going to do and he spared them. It's
a deep cry. Sometimes in anger,
sometimes in brokenness. It's a deep cry
that God would hear and he would have
mercy upon
you. The fifth one is beholding prayer.
The prayer of
adoration where you gaze in love towards
God and adore him because of who he is
and what he has done for you and I
through the cross. The single focus of
the prayer of of of beholding is adoring
God. Now, this is a difficult prayer
because even while you may have heard of
it and even while you may have been
encouraged, you need to spend some time
in your prayer time adoring God. When we
come to God in prayer, we probably spend
all of 10 seconds adoring God and then
we take out a long list of personal
needs that we have and we bring these to
him. And learning to adore God is not
something that comes easy to us. And so
we'll be talking a little more about
this this one. And I will share with you
how I have learned to spend even an hour
just adoring God. I'll tell you how to
do that. But number six is collective
prayer. When the saints gather together
and with one voice as Jesus said, "Where
two or three gather in my in my name and
they ask, it will be done in heaven."
The prayer of the saints coming together
and praying with one voice is a powerful
prayer indeed. If you could say so,
there are three things you find in
scripture that amplify prayer.
The first one you know well and it is
fasting. The second one is where there
is daring bold faith expressed in the
form of prayer. And then the third one
is when the saints gather together and
they pray together as one. Now in this
modern age of course many of our
gatherings for collective prayer are
happening virtually and this is good
because a lot more people end up praying
when you do that but there is a place
for us to gather in one place at one
time and to pray as a children of God. I
think one of the most beautiful
delightful times I saw this happening is
during the time of COVID. You remember
when COVID happened in early 2020 and
you heard there was CO in China and then
there was CO in you know in um India,
then there was CO in Italy. Then we
heard it had come to Ethiopia and next
it was here in Kenya. And we were all
listening to the news, seeing this angel
of death coming closer and closer and
closer to us. And there was a call for
collective prayer in this country. And
people on the day when the call was
made. Guys, remember seeing a photograph
of border borders, you know, stopping by
the roadside and kneeling next to their
motorbike and they spent maybe a half
hour crying to the God of heaven to
spare us from COVID. And I truly believe
that God heard those prayers.
There was a shipload of journalists who
were sent from Europe to come and
document the devastation of Africa and
of a country like Kenya. What would
happen when CO hit Kira where there is
no distancing where face masks were
being you know I'll lend you mine
because you need to go out to shop and
you know and the police will harass you.
um where where the face masks were being
used more as beard masks, you know, by
the men and all sorts of things. How was
Africa going to survive COVID? And
nobody could explain why CO did not
devastate the the populations of Africa.
I believe it was a prayer, the
collective prayer of the people of God
who gathered and asked for God's
protection.
The next is the prayer of repentance and
confession. We'll talk a little about
the daily examine. It actually is just a
word that comes from the word to examine
where you come before God and for a
little while in the day you ask God to
show you where you have heard, where you
did wrong, what you might not have done
well, where you hurt somebody else,
where you looked down on somebody and
spoke ill of them, where your tone was
wrong and harsh. And then you ask him to
forgive you. And where possible, you
also go and amend those broken
relationships that came out of your
insensitivity. The prayer of confession,
the prayer of repentance. Another is
silent prayer. This one I will tell you
is the hardest prayer that I have been
learning. I've been practicing silent
prayer for the last one year, one and a
half years now. And what silent prayer
is is that it is based on Psalm chapter
46 and verse 10. Be still and know that
I am
God where God calls us to silence. And
there's a beautiful example of this in
the book of first kings and uh chapter
19 when Elijah was running away from
Queen Jezebel because she had said that
if I lay my hands on you, I'm going to
kill you. And so Elijah run off into the
desert to hide from her. But he was in a
place where he was completely undone,
probably in depression, really, you
know, unsure about, uncertain about his
future because of this wicked queen that
was after him. And he looks for God and
God takes him into the desert and to the
mountains in the desert. And Elijah
takes residence in a cave. And God tells
him, "Come to the mouth of the cave and
I will speak with you." And so Elijah
comes to meet with God and to hear God.
And several things happen. Number one is
he
hears an earthquake taking place and the
rocks and the boulders
cracking and he thought that God had
appeared. But when he went out to look,
God was not there. The next thing that
he heard was um that that there was a
thunderstorm, a mighty thunderstorm and
he thought surely God has come and he
went to look and see God and God was not
there. And then the third time over
there was a loud explosive voice and he
goes out again to look and there is no
God. And then
finally he heard what sounded like a
quiet whisper. This is verse 12 of first
kings um chapter 19. And having heard
that gentle faint
whisper, Elijah came out of the cave and
God had arrived. God was not in the
earthquake. He was not in the
thunderstorm. He was not in the
crackling fire. He was not in the
breaking rocks. In the in the in the New
American Standard Version, this is how
it puts verse 12 of chapter 19, it says,
"After the earthquake, a fire, but the
Lord was not in the fire, and after the
fire, the sound of sheer silence."
I did not know that silence has a
sound. But it is in that sound of sheer
silence that God
spoke to
Elijah. Be still and know that I am God.
There is a prayer that God calls us to
that is a
silent
prayer where I come into God's
presence and I quiet my heart and I
quiet my mind and I quiet my
thoughts and I spend 10 or 15 or as is
my practice 30 minutes in sheer silence
listening for God to speak to
me. It is a difficult prayer but we will
talk about it. And then the ninth way is
the prayer of thanksgiving and gratitude
that scripture calls us to that it
should always be the practice in the
presence of God that I would remember to
be grateful for God and his goodness to
me and to say thank you for the many
things that he has done including
answering some of the things I have
brought up to him in prayer. If you know
the story of the 10 lepers whom Jesus
healed, you know that only
one came back to
Jesus and say thank you to Jesus. May I
suggest to you that the other nine were
consumers of
grace. They got what they wanted. They
didn't even remember to say thank you.
But this 10th one was one who was a
worshipper. And I wonder where you are.
How often do you take time to just thank
God for your health? We take our health
for granted, for the place where you
dwell, for the job that you
have. Are you a consumer who wants
blessings alone? Or do you remember to
come back to God and to say thank you?
If I say that the prayer of silence is
the hardest prayer for me, then the
prayer that is the 10th one is the one I
enjoy most and this is pondering prayer.
To ponder is to think about something
slowly and carefully for a long period
of time with
deep
consideration, weighing the options and
the possibilities and thinking through
the implications and the possible
outcomes.
Pondering prayer is where you come into
God's presence and you lay before God a
need or a problem or a question that
you're wrestling with and you have a
dialogue with God about that. And the
dialogue takes place through scriptures
that he may prompt in your heart. It may
be a stirring in your in your in your
you know in your mind. Or it could even
be that um God reminds you of something
that's happened in the past or gives you
a picture of something that he said or
did or you have a prophetic word, a
prophetic sensing and it is a slow and
quiet prayer. For some reason, even
though I did not know pondering prayer
for many of my years as a young pastor,
now that I have discovered it, I find
this is what I gravitate towards most.
And I can spend 4 hours or even a whole
day in the presence of God conversing
with him and pondering over the
decisions and the people and the needs
and the church and the organization and
the problems that I face for I enjoy
this one. This is a prayer that I always
go into God's presence with with my
prayer journal which is just a big
notebook where I write if I'm praying
for let's say Peter I will write Peter's
name at the top of the page and the
conversation with God begins and I share
with God and I actually write it out and
share with him what the need is and I
pray over Peter and I listen to see if
God will give me a word, a prophetic
word for Peter. And I write down things
and I go to the scriptures to ask God to
direct me to something that will guide
me. And it can take four or five hours.
I try and spend at least a whole
afternoon every week in pondering prayer
because I enjoy it so
much. We'll talk about these forms of
prayer through the course of the week or
rather the month. But for now, let me
take some time to just share with you a
passage that I will come back to next
week. And it is Luke 11. We'll read from
verse 1 to verse 13. But for today,
we're only going to look at half of it.
And next week we will look at the other
half and conclude that study. So Luke
chap 11 verse 1-13. I'm reading this
from the New International Version. One
day Jesus was praying in a certain
place. And when he finished, one of his
disciples said to him, "Lord, teach us
to pray." Just as John taught his
disciples, he said to them, "When you
pray, say, and you know this, can we say
together?" Because we all learned it in
primary school, and I think they still
learn it even today. Our Father, who art
in heaven, hallowed be your name. Thy
kingdom come, thy will be done on earth
as it is in heaven.
[Music]
the power and the glory forever and
ever.
Amen. This was a prayer as a model
prayer that Jesus gave to his
disciples. We'll come to the second half
of that passage um from verse 5 through
to verse 13 next week. But I want to
point out six different sections to what
is now known as the Lord's Prayer or the
Amen. Okay. Um it's called different
things in different places, but the
Lord's Prayer. And the first that you
will notice is that Jesus teaches his
disciples to begin prayer with
adoration. Our
Father who art in heaven, the sovereign
God who created this world, the Father
who has loved us and has gone to the
cross on our behalf and to spend time
adoring God for who he is and what he
has done. One of the important things
that you must remember when you pray
this way is that there is no me in
adoration. Adoration is focused on God
and God alone. And I want to challenge
you that whenever you have time to pray,
say you have 30 minutes to pray, take
the first five minutes to do nothing but
adore God for who he is.
and just voice back to God the amazing,
wonderful, beautiful things that he has
done, the creation that he has given us,
the flowers of the field, the beautiful
people that we know, the beautiful sky,
and just adore God for who he is. Gaze
into his face and adore him for who he
is. Many times our prayers begin with
me. We get up in the morning and we
pray, "Lord, my day has begun. Please
bless me this morning. My job, give me
money, me and give me me. And give me me
me." I call this a shopping list, which
is what we bring to the Lord. We have a
long list. Give me a car and give me a
good job and please help me pay that
bill and so and so is angry with me.
Please protect me. And we go through
this list that is like a shopping list
in the supermarket. And when we're done,
we say, "Okay, I'm done with prayer,
Lord. We'll see you tomorrow. Goodbye."
We we rattle off so long and so fast
that even God doesn't have an an
opportunity to speak in or put a word in
edgewise because I need to go through my
shopping list of prayer me and tell God
all the places where I need him to come
through for me. Do not begin your prayer
there. There is a need for us to share
with God the challenges and you know the
the the needs we face. But begin by
adoring
God and give him time before you pull
out the shopping list. There's a second
problem with the shopping list of prayer
that we pull out so often in that our
prayers are largely a
monologue. It's not a dialogue. We're
not talking to, you know, with God. We
are talking at God. And if you're
colleric like me, I have a mind that
also advises him. And God, you're taking
too long and you should do this sooner.
And why haven't you done this? And did
you remember that, you know, Peter has,
you know, multiple sclerosis? Do you
know what multiple sclerosis is? God.
And so I informed God on multiple
sclerosis and, you know, there are
doctors who can heal it. And I rattle
and rattle and rattle and then I say
thank you and amen and I walk off and
it's a monologue and God can't even get
a word in. Do not begin there. Begin
with
adoration. But then Jesus went on to say
this is the Lord's prayer that we just
said.
Um he went on to talk about
intercession. And in this he says, "Your
will be done, your kingdom come."
The first need that we put before God
after adoring him are the things that
pertain to the mission of
God, his church, the world, and the many
broken places there are in this world,
whether it's Gaza or it's, you know, um
uh Ukraine or other parts of the world,
we pray about these things because it is
for this very reason that Jesus came to
die on the cross. And long before I
bring my needs to God, I bring the needs
of the broken world that God loves so
much. And so the second season of prayer
in my little if it's half an hour, if
it's 15 minutes is the first is
adoration. The second is that I
intercede for the world and prioritize
the mission of God. But then the third
is supplication. To supplication just
means to ask and to put my needs or the
needs of others around me before the
presence of God. And so Jesus told them
to pray, give us this day our daily
bread. And so ask God for your need and
don't be afraid to ask for his help. But
when you do, watch out for two things.
And the first of them is not to
selfishly focus on yourself and your
needs. For some of us, we never even
have time to turn to, you know, others
who are friends and loved ones because
my own personal needs consume all the
time. I want this, I want that, can you
do this and you must give me this and
etc etc. And it becomes you know just
one more selfish focused um you know
time on myself. But then the second
thing you need to watch out for is do
not treat God as an eternal ATM.
that you can go and put in your prayer
card and the money comes out, you know,
rolling out of of uh the dis this dis
dispensing unit and then I can get my
card back because I'm going to use it
tomorrow again. Be careful that you do
not treat God as an eternal ATM for your
unending shopping list. So that's the
third. Then the fourth one Jesus told
them is forgive us our sins as we also
forgive those who sin against us. the
place of confession and
forgiveness where I ask God,
Lord, forgive me for those sins that I
committed knowing full well that I was
doing wrong and evil in your eyes and
for those things that I com sins I
committed and was not even aware that I
was done them. You know, I had I had
done wrong. Some of us um you know when
you're driving in the traffic, you're
fighting with every other driver on the
road and you're calling their name
Shenzi, you know, because they're not
driving the way you think, you know,
they should drive and they didn't let
you cut in and do all the other things
that you wanted to do. And we don't
think about it because they didn't hear
us. We don't think we have done wrong.
But in fact what has happened is that we
have shown the state of our heart inside
of us and it is not pretty and we need
to take that to the Lord and we need to
confess and we need to ask for
forgiveness even though the person will
never know that we actually spoke evil
into their life
when we were trying to edge into the
traffic. Then the fifth is spiritual
warfare and this is in verse four. And
lead us not into temptation but deliver
us from evil and from the evil one. Do
you take time to pray over your children
and what Satan would like to do to trap
them and trick them into some addiction
so that they will never know Christ?
And whether it's pornography now that is
almost impossible to rein in these
mobile units that we have
24/7 or it is drugs and the tricks that
are used by drug sellers to get you
hooked up or it is alcohol and the
pressure that is put on
teenagers to give themselves to alcohol
and to drink. Do you ever remember that
this isn't just a social, you know,
trend that is happening around us, but
that there could very well be a demonic
attempt to enslave your children, your
loved ones. Do you remember to pray for
one another's husband and wife for your
purity? Because Satan will take and
destroy that and destroy your marriage
and maybe even destroy your faith if he
can. Do you remember to ever anoint the
things that you treasure not knowing
where they come from? the house that you
live in. Um, you know, things that are
precious to you, even seeming charms
that are given to you by a loved one, an
elderly one, and it's just an innocent
necklace. And to pray for, do you even
pray for your children? When our
children were born, my wife and I took
time to look into the past of our naming
in my family and my father father who
had written down, you know, our lineage
going back I think it was something like
18 or 20 generations. One of the things
that he drew out was that three of my
ancestors were medicine men and witch
doctors. And the name is passed on from
one generation to the
next. My own name in my local language
means a
drunkard. Two of my brothers died from
alcohol. My father was a wine merchant
and as I have said before, he was his
own best
customer. And this thing called alcohol
has destroyed our family. And so when my
children were born, we prayed over this
name that would have to be bestowed on
them. We cancelled whatever curses may
come with this name that had already
destroyed part of our family. And we
chose to give them names that were
biblical and that were love names that
are seen in
scripture. There were some names we
could not avoid, but we prayed and
anointed those names before we bestowed
them on our children. We don't think
about it. We name people after somebody
historical. We do not know the character
or the spirit of that person. And so
spiritual warfare is the fifth. And then
the sixth one is to conclude by
remembering that God is
sovereign. For thine is the kingdom, the
power, and the glory forever and ever.
Amen. In other words, God, I have prayed
for all these things I have brought
before you, but at the end of the day,
you are the sovereign Lord of the
universe. The kingdom belongs to you.
The power is yours, and the glory will
come back to you forever and ever. And
so, take my prayer. Some of it was not
on point. And I don't know that because
I don't see into the future, but you do.
Take it. Hear my prayer. Change it as
only the sovereign God can do. And let
it be that I would submit to your
sovereignity, recognizing that you are
the God of the heavens and you have the
power and the glory. These are the six
things that Jesus was teaching the
disciples when he told them this is how
you
pray. So what do we do with this?
This is what I do with it. I have a
little card that writes those six things
out. And when I pray for, say I'm
praying for, you know, John, John is
going through a medical illness and it's
not clear whe whether he's going to live
or not, then what I do is I begin by
adoring God for John and what he has
made go John to be. and adoring God
because of the way that he has cared for
John, raised him up all through the
years, a beautiful person that John is.
And I spend time adoring God for this
creature, this beautiful creature that
he came and died for. But then having
done that, I move on to the second and
intercede for John and John's gifts that
God has given him to extend the kingdom
to use them for the sake of the church.
And then I want to go to supplication
and pray for John's healing and John's
health. And then I want to go to
confession and pray for those things
that I may not even fully be aware of,
but I want to confess on behalf of
John, the brokenness in his life, the
addiction that I know he struggles with
alcohol with. maybe drugs that he takes
because of some medical complication and
those drugs are destroying his liver and
he needs deliverance from that. And I
confess for God's grace upon him. But
then it could very well be that John's
illness is not actually a psychosomatic
physical illness. It is something
spiritual that is going on in John's
life. There's a story of when Jesus came
down from the mount of transfiguration
in Matthew chapter 16. He comes and
finds a father who is frustrated because
his son would get into an epileptic fit
and he'd start, you know, shaking and
sometimes he would fall into fire and
the disciples had been trying to cast
out a spirit from him. You and I in
today's world would have said that this
boy has an epileptic fit. What he needs
is medication. My dear friends, you
cannot medicate a demon. And you cannot
cast out a demon by giving those
horrible tablets and medicines that we
give to patients. Doctors, hear me,
there are some demons who will only be
exercised by prayer and fasting. And I
wonder whether as a doctor you actually
take time to pray over your patients and
to fast on their behalf because it could
very well be that what shows itself as a
physical illness is actually a demonic
presence and you need to pray because
the medicine is not going to change that
person's life. And so I pray for John
and pray, Lord, if this is something
spiritual going on, please reveal it to
us. And when I go to the hospital, I
will go with anointing oil and I will
pray over John and pray that God will
give him deliverance if in fact we're
dealing with a demonic spirit. But then
number six is that at the end of the
day, I pray that God's will be done. And
if the time has come for John to go home
and be with the Lord, then please help
him to accept that and not to fight it
and help us who love him to do the same.
And so I pray with this format that
Jesus gave through this these six
different sections as I pray for people
around uh me. Now the truth is it takes
time to
pray and there's no quick you know
prayer so to say for the hundreds of
people around you have needs. I heard of
one pastor who told his congregation I
pray for each of you by name every day.
And he had a congregation of 5,000. And
so they said what you do? Wow. Aren't we
special? He says yes I pray for each of
you by name. I take all your names and
all the visitors names every Sunday and
I get my assistant to type them out into
a long list, okay, on the computer and
then I hit the scroll button and I say,
"Hallelujah. Hallelujah. Lord, you see
all these people, Lord, bless them,
bless them, bless them." And it goes and
in one minute he's prayed for all of
them. But the truth of the matter is
that there is no shortcut to prayer.
Prayer is hard and it takes time and I
want to challenge you to create space in
your life for prayer. I've really
wrestled with this but in the last two
or so years I have I'm an older man now
and so I don't sleep well. Does anybody
hear me? Does anybody feel me? You know,
old people don't sleep well. They're
young. They just lie on even the couch
and they're gone for 8 hours, 9 hours. I
cannot sleep well. I I hear everything
going on around me. Even though I'm
supposedly asleep, I hear the dogs
barking. I hear any window crackling and
etc. I don't sleep well. And about 3
hours, 4 hours is my maximum. Nowadays,
I don't fight that. I see it as a
blessing from God. Yesterday because of
my jet lag, I went to bed at 5:00. I
could not stay awake. I went to bed at
5:00 and woke up at 9:00 in the evening
and I went and sat at my desk and the
whole night was open to prayer. I don't
fight it anymore. When I get up, I say,
"God has woken me to pray." And I will
take time to pray. And sometimes I'll go
back to bed and sleep. Sometimes I'll
catch a nap during the day, but I often
times get up at about midnight and for
about 2 or 3 hours I sit and pray before
the Lord. Prayer takes
time. Do you have that time in your
life? Now I'm young. I mean, I'm old and
I'm a pastor. I mean, what do pastors do
but pray? If you heard I don't pray,
then you'd wonder what sort of pastor is
this we have. You can't live my life.
This is the way my life is lived as a
bishop and as a pastor. But even you
must
pray. And have you created a sacred time
that nothing can interfere with? I've
tried praying during the day. But the
beautiful thing about waking up at
midnight to pray is there are no phone
calls. There's no SMSs. There is no
WhatsApp. Nothing disturbs you at all.
Everybody in the house is asleep and I
am alone with my God. and I can pray for
as long as I want to. Do you have that
time? I want to encourage you as we look
at prayer this month, begin with these
six sections of prayer. Begin to follow
them as Jesus taught us. Get yourself a
prayer journal. I'll talk to you about
how I use and how I write my prayers so
that I have a record of them. and begin
to create space in your life that is
sacred that nothing can touch and that
belongs to God and you can be alone with
him and you can pray. Next week we're
going to come back to this passage and
learn a little more in the second half
of the passage itself. For today I'd
like us to conclude with a word of
prayer and if you could come Dan and um
just lead us as we conclude our service.
Karimu, thank you so much Bishop. Thank
you. Thank you. May God continue to
bless you.
Father, we want to say thank you, King
of Glory, for you have allowed us to
learn of your word. You have allowed us
to learn about prayer. King of glory. We
do not know how to do this. And we are
weak. We are so weak. And we want to say
thank you almighty father even for the
passion. Almighty father, you have given
your servant in prayer that he can enjoy
the presence of prayer. We are asking
you that may you connect us with this
that we may enjoy prayer that we may
improve in prayer that we may relate
with you almighty father give us a
hunger and a thirst mighty Jehovah to
grow in prayer to love you and to be
what you have ordained us and now unto
him that is able to keep you from
falling and to present you faultless
before the presence of his glory with
exceeding joy to the only wise God our
savior be glory and majesty dominion and
power both now and forever more. Amen.
Amen. God bless you all. Have a nice
[Music]